Guide to the K. Leroy Irvis Papers, 1946-1995 AIS.1971.06
ULS Archives & Special Collections
K. Leroy Irvis Papers
1865-2007
1945-2006
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Irvis, K. Leroy, 1919-2006
AIS.1971.06
121.7 Linear Feet
The K. Leroy Irvis Papers document the life of one of Pennsylvania's prominent politicians. Irvis, a Democrat, represented Pittsburgh in the Pennsylvania House of Representatives from 1958-1988. Among his achievements, Irvis was elected Speaker of the House in 1977, the first African-American to hold that position in any state legislature in the United States since Reconstruction. The collection contains a wide variety of material, including correspondence, legislative material, interviews, photographs, publications, and campaign literature.
(194 boxes)
Biography
Kirkland Leroy Irvis was born in Saugerties, N.Y., December 27, 1919, son of Francis H. and Harriet Ten Broeck (Cantine) Irvis. His education includes an A.B. summa cum laude in 1938 and an M.A. in 1939 from N.Y. State Teacher's College (now SUNY) in Albany. Irvis received an LL.B. in 1954 and a J.D. in 1969 from University of Pittsburgh Law School. Irvis received the title of Doctor of Laws from both Lincoln University and The State University of New York at Albany. He also received the Owens Fellowship in Law, The Order of the Coif, and was inducted into Phi Beta Kappa.
Prior to his successful political career, Irvis worked as a teacher, Pittsburgh steel worker, editor, civil rights worker, news commentator, law clerk, assistant district attorney, civilian attaché to the War Department, and author. Irvis was a member of the Urban League of Pittsburgh, a life member of NAACP, served on the Board of Trustees of the University of Pittsburgh, and served on the Advisory Board of the University of Pittsburgh Medical School.
After his 1957 appointment as Assistant District Attorney in Pittsburgh, Irvis began his state political career. In 1958, he was elected to the Pennsylvania House of Representatives from Pittsburgh's Hill District. During this same year, his first wife, Katharyne Jones, passed away. Irvis became the Democratic Caucus Chairman in his third term in Congress, and he continued to rise through the ranks of leadership as Majority Caucus Chairman, Minority Whip, and Majority Leader. Along the way, he married Cathryn L. Edwards in 1973. In May 1977 the House unanimously elected him Speaker - the only African-American to hold the position in the United States at that time. In January 1979 the Democratic Caucus elected Irvis to serve as the Democratic Leader for the 1979-1980 session. He was re-elected to the same post for the 1981-82 session. He served again as speaker from 1983 until his retirement in 1988.
Irvis was a delegate to the 1967-1968 Pennsylvania Constitutional Convention and a delegate to the Democratic National Conventions in 1968, 1972, 1976, 1980, and 1984. During the 1980 Democratic National Convention, he served as Vice Chairman of the Pennsylvania Delegation and as Convention Co-Chairman. In 1982 Irvis was elected to serve as a member of the Democratic National Committee.
Irvis sponsored thousands of pieces of legislation addressing his concerns for education, civil rights, health, consumer protection, prison reform, housing, and governmental reform. His most noted achievements include the sponsorship and passage of legislation creating the Pennsylvania Human Relations Commission, Pennsylvania Higher Education Equal Opportunity Program, Pennsylvania Higher Education Assistance Agency, Minority Business Development Authority, House Ethics Committee, Lobbyist Registration Act, Legislative Audit Advisory Commission, House Bipartisan Management Committee, and the Pennsylvania Council on the Arts. Irvis is also credited with suggesting the creation of the Community College System in the Commonwealth. Other noteworthy education legislation Irvis sponsored included the 1966 bill that made the University of Pittsburgh, Penn State, Lincoln, and Temple state-related universities.
Among the organizations to have formally honored Irvis are the NAACP, University of Pennsylvania, Lincoln University of Pennsylvania, and Dominion Resources. The University of Pittsburgh has a K. Leroy Irvis Reading Room in Hillman Library. In 2003, the South Office Building within the Pennsylvania Capitol Complex was renamed the Speaker K. Leroy Irvis Office Building. Pennsylvania Democratic Party Chairman T. J. Rooney described Rep. Irvis as, "one of greatest legislative giants that the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania has ever seen ... [and] one of the most admired and respected Pennsylvanians we'll ever know."
Away from politics, Irvis was an accomplished artist and author. In the same year he retired (1988), Irvis wrote a book of poems called, This Land of Fire, published by Temple University. His wood sculptures have been displayed in exhibits throughout the country. Irvis died at age 86 of cancer.
Scope and Content Notes
The K. Leroy Irvis Papers document the life of one of Pennsylvania's most prominent politicians. The collection contains a wide variety of material including correspondence, legislative material, interviews, campaign literature, publications, photographs, awards, audiovisual media, and newspaper clippings. The collection documents Irvis's early career and education, his campaigns and his career as a Representative in the Pennsylvania State House of Representatives, his time as Speaker of the Pennsylvania State House, his legislative priorities and accomplishments, his personal life and hobbies, and the accolades and honors he earned during his career as a public servant. Areas of concentration in the collection include: the Pennsylvania Legislature, higher education, prison reform, housing, Pennsylvania history, senior citizens, National Democratic Conventions, Pennsylvania African-American culture and history, mental health, civil rights, and Irvis' relationship with his family and constituents.
Note: Folders 61, 62, 67, 77, 104, 105, 106, 151, and 152 from the 1974 Addition and folder 26 from the 1995 Addition have been removed from this collection.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into the following series:
I. Biography
II. Legal Career
III. Personal
IV. Legislative Files
V. Subject Files
VI. Correspondence
VII. Community
VIII. Campaigns
IX. Education
X. Political Activities
XI. Speeches and Interviews
XII. Katharyne Irvis
XIII. Cathryn Irvis
XIV. Photographs
XV. Audiovisual Material
XVI. Media
XVII. Awards, Realia, Etc.
XVIII. Publications
Throughout the collection, subseries are frequently divided by the date materials in the series were acqiured by the University of Pittburgh rather than by content. Therefore, similar or related materials may have been donated at different times and included in different subseries under the same series heading.
Access Restrictions
Folder 171 of 1971 Deposit is closed and has been removed from the collection.
Accruals
Additional material received in 1974, 1975, 1979, 1980, 1995, and 2010.
Acquisition Information
The collection, a gift from K. Leroy Irvis, consists of an original deposit in 1971.
Previous Citation
K. Leroy Irvis Papers, 1947-1995, AIS.1971.06, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
K. Leroy Irvis Papers, 1947-1995, ais 76:1, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Social action; University of Pittsburgh; African American lawyers -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; African American legislators -- Pennsylvania; African American politicians -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Civil rights -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Lawyers -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Legislation -- Pennsylvania; Legislators; Legislators -- Pennsylvania; Pennsylvania -- Politics and government; Personal papers; Politicians -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Politics; Irvis, K. Leroy, 1919-2006
- Biography, 1956-1970; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains biographical information written by or about Irvis, including correspondence with biographers and a sketch of his family background. In addition, there are awards and a career profile, as well as information on Irvis's leisure activities with model airplanes and wood carving.
  More information on Irvis's personal life may be found in Series III: Personal; further information on his hobbies and other aspects of his personal life may be found in Series III: Personal, Series XII: Katharyne Irvis, Series XIII: Cathryn Irvis, and Series XIV: Photographs.
  The series is arranged into two subseries based on the date the materials were acquired by the University of Pittsburgh.
  - Biographical Data (1971 Original Deposit), 1956-1970; 1.
    Subseries 1 contains correspondence, news releases, awards, and information Irvis's family, hobbies and professional memberships. These materials are arranged by subject.
    - Sanford R. Starobin Biography: News Release, January 1, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Family background, brief sketches, notes, etc. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence of Mark Schwartz relating to KLI biography (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Awards, honors, etc: Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Hobbies-Model aircraft: Correspondence and enclosures, 1965-1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Hobbies-Wood sculpture: Miscellaneous, including correspondence, 1956-1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence indicating local memberships, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Biography (1974 Addition), n. d.; 2.
    This subseries contains a profile of Irvis written for an unknown publication in the early 1970s.
    - Irvis Profile, no date (Box 23, Folder 1)
- Legal Career, 1955-1996; III.
  This series contains information about Irvis's legal career. Irvis was awarded a degree in law from the University of Pittsburgh School of Law in 1954. He was employed by the legal firm, Rose Schmidt and Dixon, where he oversaw a number of legal cases and eventually became Pittsburgh's Assistant District Attorney in 1957. This series includes records evidencing Irvis' law degree including his membership to the Allegheny County Bar Association, the American Bar Association, as well as his Attorney Certification. In addition to his certifications, the series contains analyses, appointments, cases, correspondence and publications. Most materials date from the 1970s and 80s, when Irvis was serving in the Pennsylvania State House of Representatives.
  More information on Irvis's legal career can be found in Series VII, Subseries 2: Irvis's Early Employment.
  - Allegheny County Bar Association, 1975 (Box 92, Folder 6)
  - Allegheny County Court Manual, 1975 (Box 92, Folder 7)
  - the Allegheny Lawyer, 1981 (Box 92, Folder 8)
  - American Bar Association, 1975 (Box 92, Folder 9)
  - American Criminal Law Review, 1996 (Box 92, Folder 10)
  - Appointments, 1976 (Box 92, Folder 11)
  - Attorney Certification, 1955 (Box 92, Folder 12)
  - Barnes, Russell, 1975 (Box 92, Folder 13)
  - Buchanon, Robert, 1976 (Box 92, Folder 14)
  - Case Roster, 1973-1976 (Box 92, Folder 15)
  - Claridge Properties, 1980 (Box 92, Folder 16)
  - Coalworkers Pneumoconiosis, 1975 (Box 92, Folder 17)
  - Comparative Analysis, Pennsylvania Bar Association, 1974 (Box 92, Folder 18)
  - Comparative Analysis, Pennsylvania Bar Association, 1974 (Box 92, Folder 19)
  - Comparative Analysis, Pennsylvania Bar Association, 1974 (Box 92, Folder 20)
  - Consolidated Coal Company, 1975-1977 (Box 92, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1975-1993 (Box 92, Folder 22)
  - Daily Time Record, 1975 (Box 92, Folder 23)
  - Eastern Associated Coal Corporation, 1976 (Box 92, Folder 24)
  - Ewing Company, 1976 (Box 92, Folder 25)
  - First Capitol Housing Partners, 1976 (Box 92, Folder 26)
  - Homayoonfar, Mohamad, 1973 (Box 92, Folder 27)
  - International Bar Association, 1978 (Box 92, Folder 28)
  - Inter-office Memos, 1975-1976 (Box 92, Folder 29)
  - Jeffries, Christina, 1975 (Box 92, Folder 30)
  - Knox, Sherman, 1976 (Box 92, Folder 31)
  - Legal Certification, 1977-1993 (Box 92, Folder 32)
  - Legal Principles, undated (Box 92, Folder 33)
  - Membership Cards, 1977-1981 (Box 92, Folder 34)
  - National Bar Association, 1993 (Box 92, Folder 35)
  - Notes and Memos, 1979-1980 (Box 92, Folder 36)
  - Ohong, Anna, 1975 (Box 92, Folder 37)
  - Pennsylvania Bar Association, 1975-1995 (Box 92, Folder 38)
  - Pennsylvania Legal Rules, 1977 (Box 92, Folder 39)
  - Petition for Reassessment, 1975 (Box 92, Folder 40)
  - Pittsburgh Courier, 1966 (Box 92, Folder 41)
  - Rose, Schmidt, and Dixon Memos, 1977-1981 (Box 92, Folder 42)
  - Schedule, 1976 (Box 92, Folder 43)
  - Sex Discrimination, 1975 (Box 92, Folder 44)
  - Slade, Trevelyn, 1958 (Box 92, Folder 45)
  - Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, 1976 (Box 92, Folder 46)
  - Thomas, Lucille, 1974 (Box 92, Folder 47)
  - United Refining Company, 1978 (Box 92, Folder 48)
  - University of Pittsburgh Alumni Directory, 1971 (Box 92, Folder 49)
  - University of Pittsburgh Alumni Directory, 1980 (Box 93, Folder 1)
  - U.S. - London Case, 1980 (Box 93, Folder 2)
  - Watson, William, 1976 (Box 93, Folder 3)
- Personal, 1939-2006; II.
  This series contains correspondence, memos, photographs and other documentation of Irvis's personal life and leisure time. Of particular note are the subseries and folders that document on his creative writing and poetry, as well as the documentation of his hobbies, including his woodcarving and model airplane building. In addition, there is some documentation of his schooling, including his time at Albany Senior High and his higher education, including articles and his M.A. thesis. There is also some documentation of Irvis's travel, including trips to Cote d'Ivoire and the Central African Republic, as well as his research and preparation for those trips and his planned Pan-African business ventures. Finally, there is some documentation of Irvis's awards and honors later in life, including his obituary, tributes, and some awards.
  This series is divided into ten subseries, divided both by subject and by the date the material was acquired by the University of Pittsburgh. There is additional personal correspondence in Series VI, Subseries iv: Correspondence (2010 addition). There is also addional material pertaining to Irvis's personal life in Series I: Biography, Series XII: Katharyne Irvis, and Series XIII: Cathryn Irvis. Some of Irvis's original sculptures and artwork may be found in this collection in Subseries XVII: Awards, Realia, Etc. Photographs of Irvis's work may be found in Series XIV: Photographs.
  - Personal Files (1971 Original Deposit), 1965-1971; 1.
    This subseries primarily contains correspondence from family and other personal matters such as contributions, subscriptions, invitations, memorabilia, and miscellaneous social and financial files. This series is arranged by subject.
    - Correspondence- Katherine Van Etten (aunt), 1965-1968 (Box 21, Folder 343)
    - Correspondence- Leora Walker (aunt), 1965-1969 (Box 21, Folder 344)
    - Correspondence- Insurance, 1967-1969 (Box 21, Folder 345)
    - Correspondence- Contributions, 1964-1969 (Box 21, Folder 346)
    - Correspondence- Subscriptions, 1966-1968 (Box 21, Folder 347)
    - Correspondence- Miscellaneous financial, 1965, 1968 (Box 21, Folder 348)
    - Correspondence- Miscellaneous social, 1965-1970 (Box 21, Folder 349)
    - Correspondence- Formal invitations, 1967-1970 (Box 21, Folder 350)
    - Correspondence- Miscellaneous, 1966-1971 (Box 21, Folder 351)
    - Law practice, 1963-1971 (Box 22, Folder 352-353)
    - Memorabilia, 1954-1969 (Box 22, Folder 354-355)
  - Office Expenses (1974 Addition), 1969-1972; 2.
    This subseries contains information about yearly expenses related to Irvis's office in the Pennsylvania State House of Representatives. There also is scant documentation of expenses of some House committees on which Irvis served.
    - Expenses, 1972 (Box 29, Folder 69-70)
  - Personal and Travel Subject Files (1979 Addition), c. 1950s; 3.
    This subseries contains Irvis's personal subject files, which contain newsclippings and programs that document his interest in theatre, history, and religion, among other topics. Irvis's interest in travel, including travel brochures and articles clipped from periodicals and magazines, is also well-represented. The subseries consists largely of correspondence, periodicals, news clippings, articles, and publications.
    - Bicentennial - Periodicals (Box 49, Folder 51)
    - Friends (Box 49, Folder 52)
    - Page One - Pittsburgh Newspaper Yearbook, 1955, 1956 (Box 49, Folder 53)
    - Pennsylvania History (Box 49, Folder 54)
    - Play Programs (Box 49, Folder 55)
    - Religious Articles (Box 49, Folder 56)
    - Space - Magazine Articles, c. 1950s (Box 49, Folder 57)
    - Travel (Box 49, Folder 58)
    - Miscellaneous Magazine Articles, c. 1950s (Box 49, Folder 59)
  - Personal (1980 Addition), 1946-1947; 4.
    This subseries documents Irvis's personal interest, including his work as an avid artist, woodcarver, model airplane builder, and writer. The series consists of publications, notes, poetry, artwork, information on model airplanes and correspondence, 1946-1947. These files are arranged by subject.
    - Publications (Box 50, Folder 7)
    - Notes for Novel (Box 50, Folder 8)
    - Poetry and School Readings (Box 50, Folder 9)
    - Artwork (Box 50, Folder 10)
    - Model Airplanes (Box 50, Folder 11)
    - Christmas Cards and Correspondence (Box 50, Folder 12)
    - Receipts (Box 50, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 50, Folder 14)
  - Personal Correspondence (1995 Addition), 1974-1993; 5.
    This subseries largely consists of Irvis's incoming personal correspondence, including letters, holiday and birthday greeting cards, and other personal correspondence. The materials are arranged chronologically by subject.
    - Personal Letters (Box 54, Folder 9)
    - Birthday Cards (Box 54, Folder 10)
    - Father's Day Cards (Box 54, Folder 11)
    - Personal Cards (Box 54, Folder 12)
    - Christmas Cards, no date (Box 55, Folder 13)
    - Christmas Cards, 1974, 1977 (Box 55, Folder 14)
    - Christmas Cards, 1984 (Box 55, Folder 15-16)
    - Christmas Cards, 1986 (Box 55, Folder 17)
    - Christmas Cards, 1987, 1989, 1993 (Box 55, Folder 18)
    - Christmas Cards, 1988 (Box 55, Folder 19)
    - Christmas Cards, 1988, 1991 (Box 56, Folder 20-21)
    - Retirement Cards (Box 56, Folder 22)
    - Thank-you Cards (Box 56, Folder 23)
    - Cards - Various, 1984-1991 (Box 56, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence - Various, 1977-1993 (Box 56, Folder 25)
    - Irvis Resumes, Applications, and Appealments (REMOVED) (Box 56, Folder 26)
  - Hobbies (1995 Addition), 1989-1991; 6.
    This subseries contains materials relating to Irvis' hobbies, including model airplanes, brass and woodwind bands, craftsman guilds, art and artists, and wood sculpting. These materials include correspondence, brochures, clippings, awards, and publications. Of particular note is the folder which contains brochures, programs, and awards for shows of Irvis' wood sculptures.
    Some of Irvis's original sculptures and artwork may be found in this collection in Subseries XVII: Awards, Realia, Etc. Photographs of Irvis's work may be found in Series XIV: Photographs.
    - Airplanes / ARC (Box 67, Folder 132)
    - Airplanes - ARCS (Box 67, Folder 133)
    - American Wind Waterways Orchestra (AWWO) (Box 67, Folder 134)
    - AWWO, 1989 (Box 68, Folder 135)
    - Articles on KLI (Box 68, Folder 136)
    - ArtSourceBook: A Directory of Minority Artists in Pa. (Box 68, Folder 137)
    - Biography - KLI, notes (Box 68, Folder 138)
    - Manchester Craftsmen Guild, 1989-1991 (Box 68, Folder 139)
    - Pittsburgh Voyager (Box 68, Folder 140)
    - River City Brass Band, Photos, 1991 (Box 68, Folder 141)
    - KLI - Sculpture (Box 68, Folder 142)
  - K. Leroy Irvis' Writings (1995 Addition), 1939-1952; 7.
    This subseries documents Irvis's work as a writer; Irvis wrote academic research, fiction, essays, and poetry throughout his life. The subseries includes correspondence with publishers, manuscripts, publications, clippings, and notebooks containing fiction, poetry, notes, observations, and Irvis's M.A. thesis. The majority of these writing are from Irvis' youth and college years. These materials are arranged by subject.
    - Fiction - A Hollow Tree Standing (Box 82, Folder 281-282)
    - Poetry - The Land of Fire (Box 82, Folder 283-284)
    - Various Notes, etc. (Box 82, Folder 285)
    - Poetry (Box 82, Folder 286-288)
    - Poetry (Box 83, Folder 289-290)
    - Term Paper - Negro Folk Tales (Box 83, Folder 291)
    - Literature - Ideas and Notes (Box 83, Folder 292)
    - Poetry - Proofs (Box 83, Folder 293-294)
    - Poetry, Writings, Copyright Forms (Box 83, Folder 295)
    - Poetry - Lions and Great Bronze Bars (Box 84, Folder 296-297)
    - Dust on Her Eyes Manuscript (Box 84, Folder 298)
    - Correspondence from Publishers and Agents, 1947-1952 (Box 84, Folder 299)
    - Master's Thesis - The Negro in the Civil War Ballads, 1939 (Box 84, Folder 300)
    - Notebooks (Box 84, Folder 300A)
      Missing Title
      Afrique Afrique! (black)
      For Kadim: A Love Song (white)
      Miscellaneous poems (blue)
      Notes 4 - KLI's notes for his fiction and poetry writing, observations of street vocabulary and dialect
      History of Robert Lee Vaughn, 1879-1940
  - Personal (2010 Addition), 1938-2006; 8.
    The material in this subseries relates to Irvis's personal interests including model airplane and RC aeronautics clubs, art, sculpture and woodcarving. It contains notes and sketches completed by Irvis throughout his lifetime, childhood mementos, and membership cards for the many organizations to which he belonged. This subseries is arranged alphabetically by subject.
    - Academy of Model Aeronautics, 1992 (Box 90, Folder 1)
    - Acknowledgements, 1999 (Box 90, Folder 2)
    - Aero Radio Control Society, 1982-2003 (Box 90, Folder 3)
    - Air Trails, 1976-1978 (Box 90, Folder 4)
    - Airplane Designs, 1955 (Box 90, Folder 5)
    - Albany Photographs, 2004 (Box 90, Folder 6)
    - Albany Senior High, 1934 (Box 90, Folder 7)
    - Archives, 2004 (Box 90, Folder 8)
    - Artsource Book, 1983 (Box 90, Folder 9)
    - Artwork, 1980-2000 (Box 90, Folder 10)
    - Biographical Information, 1993 (Box 90, Folder 11)
    - Biographical Sketch from Grandchild, 2003 (Box 90, Folder 12)
    - Birthday, 1972 (Box 90, Folder 13)
    - Calendar, 1973 (Box 90, Folder 14)
    - Calendar, 1999 (Box 90, Folder 15)
    - Carving Magazine, 2005 (Box 90, Folder 16)
    - Certificates and Awards, 1939-1981 (Box 90, Folder 17)
    - Chip Chats, 1980 (Box 90, Folder 18)
    - Citations, 1999 (Box 90, Folder 19)
    - Citizens Radio Station License, 1975 (Box 90, Folder 20)
    - Commemorations, 2006 (Box 90, Folder 21)
    - Condolences, 2006 (Box 90, Folder 22)
    - Constitution of the USSR, 1977 (Box 90, Folder 23)
    - COSERV, 1978 (Box 90, Folder 24)
    - Datebooks, 1979-1985 (Box 90, Folder 25)
    - Datebooks, 1972-1982 (Box 90, Folder 26)
    - Datebook, 1990 (Box 90, Folder 27)
    - Datebook, 1991 (Box 90, Folder 28)
    - Family Calendar, 1998 (Box 90, Folder 29)
    - Fly Paper, 1988 (Box 90, Folder 30)
    - Flying Ace, 1939-1989 (Box 90, Folder 31)
    - Friends, undated (Box 90, Folder 32)
    - Funeral, 2006 (Box 90, Folder 33)
    - Government in Exile, 1995 (Box 90, Folder 34)
    - Grandchildren, 1985 (Box 90, Folder 35)
    - Grandchildren, 1996-2005 (Box 90, Folder 36)
    - Guestbook, 1986 (Box 90, Folder 37)
    - House of Representatives Memorial Ceremony, 2006 (Box 90, Folder 38)
    - Hubbard, Vera, 1999 (Box 90, Folder 39)
    - Interview Transcript, 1981 (Box 90, Folder 40-41)
    - Irvis, Reginald, 2002 (Box 90, Folder 42)
    - KLI Productions, 1998 (Box 90, Folder 43)